and welcome to the Rob called bottom up
show available on Pacifica Radio Network
progressive radio network I Heart Radio
iTunes stitcher SoundCloud and a top n
news.com sled / podcasts big
conversation is is about the whistle
blower right now the anonymous whistle
blower who reported on Trump's
conversation with the president of
Ukraine and there are some interesting
debate over what the story is with this
guy so I invited former CIA agent John
Kiriakou who I know because he's a
whistleblower and he blew the whistle on
torture by the United States which ended
up putting him in jail which is the way
the United States treats a lot of people
who cast light on the truth who are
whistleblowers so it's great to have you
back on the show thanks good to see you
again oh it's a pleasure so there
there's an interesting collection of
conversations around this and one of the
reasons I had you on was because some
people are really criticizing this guy
yeah and I just would like your take on
this whistleblower is he really a
whistleblower if he's working for the
CIA and whistleblowing on the president
people are saying that whistleblowers
are people who whistled make blow the
whistle on their employer you know I'm
of two minds on this whole issue first
of all the guy does does meet the
definition of whistleblowing which is
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud abuse illegality or threats to the
public health or public safety if you
become aware of a violation of the law
and you go to whomever your chain of
command the Inspector General the
congressional oversight committees yes
that's the definition of whistleblowing
but we don't really know anything about
this guy and I'm not entirely convinced
that it's one person and I'll tell you
why in 1996 I was serving overseas and I
became aware of a very
large but illegal campaign contribution
to the Dole presidential campaign and so
I reported it I reported it to the CIA
Inspector General they took the
information they did an investigation
they deemed it to be credible and they
sent it to the Federal Election
Commission end of story
that's a normal whistleblower disclosure
what we have here is a guy who became
aware of the information we're not
really sure how now it appears to be
secondhand which is perfectly fine he
went through his chain of command and
then this Pandora's Box opened where
from the chain of command his immediate
supervisors it went to the attorneys at
the General Counsel it went up through
the the leadership it went to Gena has
full it went to the IG it went to every
Tom Dick and Harry it seems at every
senior level of the CIA and then it went
to odn eyes inspector general the odni
inspector general according to the law
is supposed to investigate it and if he
deems it truthful he's supposed to send
it to the oversight committees that's
what the law says and that's how these
things are investigated but it wasn't
sent to the oversight committees it was
sent to the Justice Department well the
law doesn't say investigate it and then
send it to the Justice Department for
political advice and so you know on the
one hand this seems to be inappropriate
behavior on the part of the president on
the other hand I will not jump onto the
CIA bandwagon and and declare that it's
the CIA that's the guardian of our
democracy we just don't have the facts
and I know what the CIA's like they lied
about torture they lied about rendition
they lied about secret prisons they lied
about hacking into the Senate
intelligence committees computer system
they lie about everything so why should
we take their word for this we've had
this conversation before as a CIA agent
you're trained to lie exactly everybody
in the building is trained to lie you
get promoted based on how well you lie
so why in the world would I now believe
them on this but you believe the
whistleblower but not damn her I'm not
even saying that I I mean if I take it
at face value I'm really conflicted
about this if I take it at face value
and I concede that there was an analyst
who had served at the White House at the
National Security Council and this
analyst believes that he came across
this information okay
then then I believe that he did the
right thing by reporting it but then I
believe that the agency as an
organization did exactly the wrong thing
by taking over the whole process you
know I don't care what the CIA says that
there's no such thing as a deep state
that they have no beef with Donald Trump
I don't believe any of that you remember
you remember Chuck Schumer warned Donald
Trump in 2017 of exactly this you can't
mess with the intelligence services
because they have nine ways from Sunday
to ruin you and I think that's what
we're seeing here so it's now I'm not
clear that you you said that you thought
there may be more than one person behind
this whistleblower yes let me explain
that I do not think this is one person I
think this is a group of people being
fronted by one person and it's because
you read the whistleblower complaint and
it does not read like a whistleblower
complaint I went through the same
analytic training at the CIA that this
guy went through there's a certain
writing style that the CIA beats in to
you I still write in that style even
though I've been gone from the CIA for
15 years and I've been out of analysis
for 22 I still write in that style
because it is just beaten into you this
whistleblower report is not in the CIA
writing style this whistleblower report
was written by a committee and that
leads me to believe that the lawyers had
their chop on it the CIA leadership had
its chop on it and that it was a group
of analysts that each contributed to it
so I believe that there is not one
whistleblower
I believe that there are many people who
work
support now yeah did you get a look at
Caitlyn Johnstone's article yeah I sure
did what's your response to that I mean
she basically is brutal she she
basically says this guy is the CIA guy
CIA is horrible all intelligence
agencies and people are horrible I mean
pretty much and and and the other part
of the article is we should be paying
attention to the good whistleblowers
like Chelsea Chelsea Manning and Ed
Snowden and and those folks and you but
but and Bill Binney and Tom strike and
and and Jessica around it's jesselyn
Radack
yeah uh but she's brutal I mean she's
brutal I tweeted the piece when it came
out just because she said in so few
words what so many of us have thought I
had a I had a an experience at MSNBC two
days ago that was it's just indicative
of the situation that we face now where
I went on MSNBC on to the re Melbourne
show they never ran the clip they ended
up Killian they killed it for a reason
first of all they introduced me as
former CIA officer and convicted felon
John Kiriakou not a word about
whistleblowing it was utterly irrelevant
that I'm a convicted felon when they
invited me to come on and talk about the
whistleblower so what they wanted was
for me to criticize the president and
say how great the whistleblower is and
how great the CIA was for going forward
with this information and I told them
what I just told you that we really
don't know what the situation is yet
we're getting bits and pieces some
released from the White House some
released by the Oversight Committee and
some of it probably leaked to the press
by the CIA so I said we really don't
know if we should trust this
whistleblower that didn't fit into their
narrative another complaint that I had
was following my arrest
it took my lawyers especially jesselyn
Radack one year from January of 2012 to
Jay
weary of 2013 to get CNN and MSNBC to
stop calling me
CIA leaker John Kiriakou and to start
calling me
CIA whistleblower John Kiriakou now see
is CNN ever since then has called me a
whistleblower and Fox for whatever
reason has always referred to me as a
whistleblower MSNBC still calls me a
leaker and on the Rachel Maddow Show she
referred to me as John Kiriakou who
styles himself a whistleblower we've got
the mainstream networks here that have
their own agenda and are trying to
promote that agenda regardless of what
the facts are and regardless of what the
information is when the facts change Wow
yeah and then there's Adam Schiff now
the word is that this whistleblower
spoke to shift before we reported yeah
that's the latest what's your take on
that the whistleblower is certainly
entitled to do so if you feel that you
are not getting satisfaction in your
home agency the law permits you to go to
the oversight committees that's why the
staff members have such high level
clearances in the case of Tom Drake at
NSA Tom went to his Inspector General he
went to the General Counsel he went to
the DoD Inspector General he didn't get
any satisfaction and so he went to the
Oversight Committee you can do that and
a lot of whistleblowers do do that you
know I thinking about Tom I I've had Tom
on a couple times he went through hell
on yeah terrible experience and I and I
believe he's still really struggling he
I do you think this whistleblowers gonna
go through hell it doesn't I mean I I
wonder I mean I mean if it Trump has his
way he will but if Trump has his way the
whistleblower is gonna be executed on a
gallows on some military base somewhere
of course that's never gonna happen but
if this is a legitimate whistleblower
yes I think his career is finished
because look at it this way if you're a
CIA manager
what's to keep you from saying this guy
ratted out the President of the United
States
what's him to what's to keep him from
ratting out me or us as an organization
you know he doesn't like a conversation
that the president has with Ukraine
right now what if he doesn't like the
rendition program tomorrow what if he
doesn't like you know something akin to
a torture program what if he doesn't
like hacking into the Senate
intelligence committees computer systems
whatever the the issue happens to be can
they trust this guy they told me that
one of my problems was I couldn't keep
my big mouth shut when I went public
with the torture program is that what
they're gonna say about this guy but
wait a second you you just a couple
minutes ago premise that maybe this was
a committee project and that other
people that were talking back even
earlier this is what I was saying we
don't know is this a legitimate
whistleblower is this a whistleblowing
by committee or is this a CIA operation
against the president we truly don't
know now if it's whistleblowing by
committee or a cái a CIA operation
against the president he's probably not
gonna be in much trouble correct unless
they I'm sure they've got lots of black
funds available so they could pay him
off for the rest of his life and oh no
but they do that kind of thing what they
what I could see them doing is what
might my guess is if he's already served
at the White House he's either a gs-15
or he's an sis one senior intelligence
service one so he probably already has
the time in for retirement but what they
can do is what they do so many people as
a reward for a good long career is you
make him a scholar in residence at
whatever college or university he
graduated from and you let him do two
three four years there then he takes the
full pension and he goes away quietly
they do that all the time all the time
okay but but so let's let's take a step
back now and Trump is trying to destroy
this guy
and his backers and supporters are yes
and some people on the left are too like
I think Caitlyn Johnstone is is
basically pretty negative about him yes
what effect does that have on other
whistleblowers I mean I've been involved
with the whistleblower community for
over ten years now and it's hard enough
for somebody to make a decision to do
what it takes to be a whistleblower
which generally means destroy your life
lose your job maybe go into debt for
million dollars or more as you did look
at it yeah so what if I mean all this
media attention on this whistleblower it
is it gonna intimidate is it gonna scare
off whistleblowers we desperately need
whistleblowers absolutely I agree with
you on all those points Scott Cheney at
the New York Times said that on the day
of my arrest every one of the New York
Times national security sources went
silent and that's exactly what the goal
is in 99% of these whistleblower cases
that's why the prosecutions are so
difficult I mean difficult for the
whistleblower because the point isn't
even necessarily take to have you
sentenced to a long stretch in prison
the point is to ruin you so that it acts
as a deterrent for other people who
might be thinking of blowing the whistle
I can't tell you how many people former
CIA people have told me that you know
they thought about reporting on X Y & Z
but then they saw what happened to me a
million dollars in debt my wife takes
off I lose my house I lose my job I lose
my clearance I'll never work in
government or national security again
it's taken me all these years to get
back on my feet nobody wants to live
like that they actively ruin you that's
all that's a part of the program nobody
wants that so is there anything that can
be done to flip this around so that this
whistleblowers report and the response
to it can actually encourage
whistleblowers
well it's kind of hard to say with a
president who likes to just throw
grenades into the middle of the room I
will say that again I'm going to preface
it if this is a legitimate whistleblower
the CIA did the right thing in reporting
the information Odie and I did not do
the right thing by sending the
information to the Justice Department it
should have just sent it directly to the
Oversight Committee and the president
should have kept his big mouth shut so
the the the mo for for reporting this
kind of thing actually didn't work in
this case and it didn't work because
both odni and the White House decided
that they didn't want it to work for
though for the system to work it has to
go exactly the way that the law calls
for it to go otherwise there aren't
going to be whistleblowers because
people aren't going to want to take the
risk so when the odni violated the law
and went to the DOJ instead of Congress
are there consequences for that
no no the the acting D&I said that that
this was unprecedented territory which
is true and you know this is one of
those laws in the books that will never
be prosecuted just like
over-classification
is actually a felony and it's never ever
been prosecuted nor will it ever be so
no it's one of those things that's just
going to be ignored and lost in the in
the greater context of of this case what
would you expect to see happen as this
story unfolds in terms of the
whistleblower the whistleblower I think
is going to have to testify at some
point and I would bet my next paycheck
that it would be in a classified venue
in a closed session that's the only way
to get the information all of the
information all of the background
including what led to the writing of the
report in the first place on the record
with that said the Republicans are
extraordin
Merilee hostile to this whistleblower
and i wouldn't be surprised if the
whistleblowers identity is leaked that's
what I would think if it's leaked then
we we move on to an entirely different
plane you know when I went public on
torture in December of 2007 I got
hundreds literally hundreds of pieces of
hate mail and hate email but the FBI
called me one day and said that they had
three what they described as three
credible threats on my life and and one
of them actually mentioned my children
and my address and so they urged me to
leave town so I took my family to Cancun
for a week and the FBI called and said
that they had taken care of everything
that they had interviewed these people
they were just you know local lunatics
and there was no real threat we came
back well we're in a far far more
politically charged environment now than
we were in 2007 and if this guy's
identity is revealed you know how many
Pro Trump nuts there are out there I
mean we see at campaign rallies Trump
supporters beating up journalists and
beating up protesters and the president
egging them on what's you know you I
watched your or listen to your interview
with Kevin ghost Allah overshadow FX a
great interview and Kevin's a great guy
former editor at op-ed news by the way
and you said that there's enough
information already that probably people
down at the CIA know who he is
in five minutes you can figure it less
than five minutes there are only so many
oh my wait so it's it's not if we find
out who he is its web yeah in fact I had
a call last night from a CIA friend of
mine who told me the name and I said my
god is it is it out already and he said
no but everybody in the building figured
it out it only took but a minute right
the New York Times article last week
that described the guy was was easily
enough information to identify them it
just hasn't been leaked yet and I hope
it's not leaked
good luck yeah and so it's a him yes Wow
well I'm not even I'm dying a curiosity
but I don't want to mess up his life any
more than it's he's got in store for him
this was a major decision that he took
to do this I mean he had to have known
the risks before he went into it because
there's precedent I'm sure he saw what
happened to Tom Drake and Bill Binney
and Chelsea Manning and Ed Snowden and
me and you know I I spoke with an
Israeli journalist years ago who wrote a
book it was a psychological profile of
four twentieth-century whistleblowers
and he came to two conclusions that were
fascinating to me one was that
whistleblowers have a far more highly
developed sense of right and wrong than
the general public of general population
right very clearly defined sense of
right and wrong the other thing is that
whistleblowers never make a financial
comeback they believe in their hearts
they do the right thing
but then they're ruined financially and
they never recover from it that's I
would say that's true for government
whistleblowers so I mean there are some
whistleblowers in corporations for
example where I can get rewards actually
for damaged
percentages of damages and things like
that Protection Act yes yeah now Chuck
Grassley has added his words what's your
take on what he had to say you know you
can count the number of you can count
the number of Pro whistleblower members
of Congress on one finger and that is
Chuck Grassley the senior senator from
Iowa Grassley was the author of The
Whistleblower Protection Act he was the
author of the National Security
Whistleblower Protection Act
he speaks every year at the national
whistleblower Center's annual luncheon
he's the only guy that's serious about
protecting whistleblowers and you can't
keep people safe with the support of one
member of Congress
well I mean I know I've been to a number
of these luncheons and events and and
he's not the only one but they're very
rare you know there are one or two
junior members of Congress I submit of
the house but in terms of legislative
authority only Grassley can push some of
these things through the system and and
get him signed into law that's why we
have these whistleblower protection laws
then what he did was he made an
announcement getting behind this
whistleblower but yes he did I mean he
had to it it's his law the whistleblower
invoked his law to protect himself so
Grassley was sort of pushed into it now
Grassley is not a member of the
Intelligence Committee so Grassley
doesn't have the the answers to the
questions that we are asking as to
whether or not this is a legitimate
whistleblower he just has to sort of go
with it until proven otherwise
okay so I want to continue on the line
of questioning that I had with you about
what's going to happen with this guy you
started off by telling us about what
happened with you and that it'll be
worse with him in terms of threats oh I
think what else what what is the what's
going to happen to him in terms of the
media in terms of government in terms of
in terms of government I think he's
going to be okay because he did what the
law called for him to do he went through
the chain of command he's not going to
lose his pension he's not going to get
fired from his job if he's outed he's
going to have some personal problems but
I don't think he'll have professional
problems with that said as I noted
earlier there are going to be people
inside the CIA that are going to
question whether or not to trust him
because he ratted out the President of
the United States and otherwise you know
the the the path of the whistleblower is
a very very lonely one like I said
any of us have gone bankrupt many of us
have lost our families we've lost our
pensions we lost our security clearances
we lost our ability to work in
government and that's with or without
convictions that's just by virtue of the
fact that you went public in the first
place so I think that he desperately
would want to see this remain within the
chain of command and within the
Intelligence Committee the Oversight
Committee and that his identity never be
exposed you know when you talk about it
remaining within the chain of command
that just doesn't feel like the regular
whistleblower process though not at all
it doesn't at all feel like the
whistleblower process people ask me all
the time why I didn't go through the
chain of command
they asked me this on MSNBC just the
other night and the answer is an easy
one you know on torture my chain of
command created the torture program my
chain of command implemented the torture
program well why didn't you go to the
Oversight Committee because the
oversight committees approved of the
torture program and then financed it so
my only alternative was to go to the
media so it's just impossible to go
through the chain of command
now you've speculated that he's probably
a gs-15 or an sis one yes because of his
placement yes any more about what kind
of CIA operative or agent gets placed in
the White House what are the criteria
what is the experience what is the job
there good question so the National
Security Council has several slots in
every geographic area that are reserved
for CIA analysts they also have several
slots reserved for for high-performing
State Department foreign service
officers and it's because the NSC is
both a policy and an intelligence organ
and so if you are a respected
high-performing gs-14 or gs-15 you go to
the White House for two years you might
be able to extend it to three years and
you generally come back to a promotion
and that promotion would be to gs-15 or
to the senior intelligence
service sis level 1 it's a job that many
many analysts aspire to and to make the
senior intelligence service the internal
rule is that you have to do a rotation
in another Directorate and a rotation in
the policy community so this is the
policy rotation and it brings you into
direct daily contact with the National
Security Advisor the deputy national
security adviser and frequently with the
president himself and what's the job
there it's coming up with policy it's
using the CIA's analysis to better
inform policy its the Nexus really of
intelligence and policy and who would
this agent be working with what other
people well there are a lot of political
appointees certainly at the NSC but
generally he would be working with a
pretty even mix of CIA State Foreign
Service and DOD uniformed personnel and
what kind of policy would it be working
on would be some examples foreign policy
I mean it's as simple as that so
everyone has unique foreign policy and
you got a you got to come up with it and
come up with intelligence to support it
no matter what it is now we've heard
that there were 20 people in that phone
call and I don't believe that I saw that
and and I don't believe that for a
minute
usually there are four on rare occasions
there are five people on that phone call
you're going to have the Secretary of
State the National Security Advisor the
chief of staff the the NSC expert for
whatever the issue happens to be and
maybe if it's if it's somebody like
Vladimir Putin somebody that important
you might have the CIA director on the
line as well but you know these routine
calls they take place every day all day
you can't have 20 people wasting their
time on a call with a prime minister of
XYZ country that doesn't make any sense
and we're told that he so so
basically somebody else who was on the
call had to inform him I think so you
know this is another thing that nobody's
really discussing these memos they're
called men cons memoranda of
conversations they're write-ups of the
call the president said this the Prime
Minister said that and the president
said this and the PM said the other
thing these are usually very tightly
held and they do not leave the NSC so
the fact that a CIA analyst had access
to one of these memos tells me that
somebody at the White House gave it to
her because when I was an analyst we
never ever had access to write-ups of
the president's conversations with
anybody
those were internal NSC documents not to
leave NSC
okay.i he told me you had to go to
another yes forgive me it starts in
three minutes any any final words you
know this is a story that is literally
breaking by the day it's hard to keep
all the details clear but we really need
to we need to read all these articles we
need to come to our own conclusions
somebody's lying and I'm wondering if
it's multiple people who are lying so
far it's gonna be a while before we get
to the truth John Kiriakou former CIA
agent whistleblower American Hero
thank you for being on the show again
appreciate the rock bottom up though
thank you thanks for having me it's a
pleasure it's always a pleasure to have
you thank you thanks buddy take care